Good morning, everyone.
صباح الخير جميعًا.
When I was first asked to do a TED Talk,
عندما طُلب مني إلقاء محادثة TED،
I Googled to try and find out a little bit more about,
بحثت في جوجل لمحاولة معرفة القليل عن،
you know, how it felt to be giving one.
كما تعلمون، كيف يبدو إلقاء حديث.
And one of the first things I read was a speaker in the States
وأحد أول الأمور التي قرأتها كان عن مُتحدثة في الولايات المتحدة
saying that she felt fine until she came onstage,
قالت أنها شعرت على نحوٍ جيد إلى أن صعدت للمسرح،
and then she saw the timer ticking down.
ورأت المؤقت يقوم بالعد تنازليًا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And it reminded her of a bomb.
فذكرها ذلك بالقنبلة.
I was thinking, "That's the last thing I need."
فقلت لنفسي: "هذا آخر أمر أحتاجه."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Anyway, it's a great privilege to be here.
على أي حال، إنه لشرف عظيم أن أكون هنا.
I think it's a bit of a joke
أعتقد أنه لأمر مضحك قليلًا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We're not renowned for our words,
نحنُ لسنا مشهورين بفصاحتنا،
and I spent the last 40 years hiding behind a camera
فقد قضيت آخر 40 سنة مختبئًا خلف الكاميرا
so I didn't have to speak.
ولذلك لم يكن علي أن أتحدث.
But I'm here today, and what I want to talk about are stories
ولكن أنا هنا اليوم، وما أود الحديث عنه هو القصص
and the importance of stories to me
وأهمية القصص بالنسبة لي
and, I think, the importance of stories to everybody.
ولجميع الناس على ما أعتقد.
I'm sure today you'll hear a lot of stories
أنا متأكد أنك ستسمع اليوم الكثير من القصص
and, by listening to other people's stories,
وبالإستماع إلى قصص الناس،
I think we can learn about the world, about other people
أعتقد أنه بإمكاننا أن نتعلم عن العالم وعن الأشخاص الآخرين
and get a better understanding.
وأن نفهم بشكل أفضل.
So I want to talk about three stories that I've done as a photographer,
لذلك أريد أن أتحدث عن ثلاث قصص وثقتها كمصور،
and how they've inspired me,
وكيف قامت بإلهامي،
and how, in my life, I've become a part of the stories
وكيف أصبحتُ جزءًا من هذه القصص
that I document myself.
التي قمت بتوثيقها بنفسي.
As John said, I was a fashion photographer
كما قال جون، كنت مصور أزياء
and music photographer for 10 years.
ومصور موسيقي لأكثر من 10 سنوات.
I enjoyed it, I had a lot of fun,
لقد كان الأمر ممتعًا ومرحًا،
but always wanted to do something more with my work.
ولكنني رغبت دائمًا بفعل شيء أفضل بعملي.
And storytelling was always something I wanted to do.
ودائمًا ما كان سرد القصص أمر أود فعله.
So 10 years ago, I set out to travel the world,
لذلك منذ 10 سنوات، قررت أن أسافر حول العالم،
to go and photograph other people in their situations
لأذهب وأصور مواقف الآخرين
and to record their stories, to bring them back,
وأوثق قصصهم، وأنشرها،
so that other people might understand.
بحيث يفهمها الآخرون.
But this didn't happen overnight.
ولكن هذا لم يحدث بين عشيةٍ وضحاها.
When I worked as a music photographer and a fashion photographer,
عندما كنت أعمل كمصور موسيقي ومصور أزياء،
I always had this nagging feeling that there was something missing,
كان لدي دائمًا هذا الشعور المزعج بأن هناك شيء ناقص،
that I wasn't quite using my skills productively.
شعور بأني لم أكن أستخدم مهاراتي بشكل جيد.
And it may seem very obvious, the link, now,
ومع أنه واضح جدًا الآن،
but at the time, I couldn't really work out
ولكن في ذلك الوقت، لم أستطع معرفة
how could I use my photography to do something useful.
كيف يمكنني استخدام تصويري لفعل شيء مفيد.
So I gave up photography.
لذلك تخليت عن التصوير.
I walked away from it completely and decided to do care work.
تركت الأمر تمامًا وقررت أن أقوم بأعمال الرعاية.
As a care worker, I started looking after a young guy called Nick.
وكشخص يعمل في الرعاية، بدأت برعاية شاب يدعى نيك.
Nick has autism, very severe autism.
نيك مصاب بالتوحد، توحد شديد جدًا.
But over the years of looking after him, we became very close friends.
ولكن بعد سنين من رعايته، أصبحنا أصدقاء مقربين.
I would give him a 24-hour care,
كنت أقدم له رعاية على مدار اليوم،
we would go off and do things from swimming, going for walks ...
كنا نمارس جميع النشاطات من السباحة، المشي ...
all sorts.
كل الأنواع.
Bit by bit, though, as I got to know him better,
تدريجيًا، ومع معرفتي له بشكل أفضل،
I realized that his story wasn't being told.
أدركت أن لا أحد يعرف قصته.
He self-harmed, he would punch himself quite a lot in the face.
فهو يقوم بإيذاء نفسه، فكان يلكم نفسه كثيرًا في الوجه.
And nobody really got to see that.
ولم يتح لأحد رؤية ذلك.
So this is Nick.
هذا هو نيك.
He used to describe his life as living downstairs at a party.
اعتاد أن يصف حياته كأنه يعيش وفوقه حفلة.
He said he could hear the party in the kitchen,
قال أنه يمكنه سماع صوت الحفلة في المطبخ،
but he felt like he was always trapped in the basement,
بينما يكون هو محاصرًا فى القبو،
in his own little world,
في عالمه الصغير،
wanting to be part of the party but not able to walk upstairs.
يريد أن يكون جزء من الحفلة ولكنه غير قادر على الصعود للطابق العلوي.
So I documented his life.
لذلك قمت بتوثيق حياته.
I started to photograph it,
بدأت بتصويرها،
not really with any intention of doing anything with the pictures,
بدون أي نية لفعل أي شيء بالصور،
but just as a way of recording.
لكن فقط كطريقة لتسجيلها.
And as I started doing that, I realized that I could tell somebody's story
وخلال فعلي لذلك، أدركت أني أستطيع نقل قصص الناس
through my photographs.
من خلال صوري.
As I said, Nick would self-harm.
كما قلت، نيك كان يقوم بأذية نفسه.
He would punch himself in the face.
كان يلكم نفسه في وجهه.
And nobody really got to see that.
ولم يتح لأحد فعلًا رؤية ذلك.
As we built up a kind of closer friendship,
ومع توطيد صداقتنا،
he finally would allow me to actually see him doing this
سمح لي أخيرًا أن أشاهده وهو يفعل ذلك
and to document it.
وأن أوثقه.
It was a moment of trust.
لقد كانت لحظة ثقة.
The social services were not particularly good at helping Nick,
لم تكن الخدمات الاجتماعية تساعد نيك بشكل جيد،
and they said that he wouldn't be self-harming as bad as we said.
ولم يصدقوا أنه قادر على إيذاء نفسه للدرجة التي أبلغناهم بها.
So one day, I took a photograph of when he'd really been self-harming.
لذلك في أحد الأيام، التقطت صورة له وهو يقوم بإيذاء نفسه.
We took that to the social services,
وأخذناها للخدمات الاجتماعية،
and their reaction was immediately incredibly different,
وعلى الفور، كان رد فعلهم مختلفًا جدًا،
and they managed to get a lot of help.
فتدبروا أمر حصوله على مساعدة أكثر.
And I'm glad to say now, eight years later,
وأنا سعيد بأن أقول الآن، وبعد ثمان سنوات،
I actually spoke to Nick last night,
أنني تحدثت لنيك البارحة،
and he wanted to let me know that he was feeling a lot better,
وأخبرني أنه يشعر بتحسن كبير،
and he doesn't do the self-harming anymore.
وأنه لا يقوم بإيذاء نفسه الآن.
And in some small way, I hope that the photographs
وآمل أن تكون الصور قد ساهمت، ولو بشكل بسيط،
was a part of that process.
في عملية التحسن.
The main thing it did is it inspired me to go out with my camera
الشيء الأساسي الذي فعلته هو أن ألهمتني للخروج ومعي كاميرتي
and to tell other people's stories.
وأروي قصص الآخرين.
One of the stories I did was in Kutupalong,
كانت إحدى القصص في كوتبالونج،
on the border of Burma and Bangladesh.
على حدود بورما وبنغلاديش.
Here, the Rohingyas refugees have been left,
هناك، حيث تُرك لاجئو الروهينجا،
pretty much to rot,
غالبًا ليتعفنوا،
for over 20 years.
لأكثر من 20 سنة.
This is a picture of the unofficial camp.
هذه صورة للمخيم غير الرسمي.
At the top, you can see the official UN camp.
في الأعلى، تستطيع رؤية مخيم الأمم المتحدة الرسمي.
All these huts are the unofficial camps.
جميع هذه الأكواخ هي مخيمات غير رسمية.
Literally, the raw sewage runs through the camp.
حرفيًا، مياه الصرف الصحي تمر خلال المخيم.
The people there have been forgotten,
الناس هناك تم نسيانهم،
so I thought it was important to go and document their stories.
لذلك فكرت أن أذهب وأوثق قصصهم.
So I arranged with the village elder;
وقمت بالتنسيق مع كبير القرية.
the people would come along the next day,
بحيث يأتي الناس في اليوم التالي،
and I would take portraits of all these people
وألتقط صورًا لهم
and record their stories.
وأسجل قصصهم.
So as the time went on, I turned up in the morning,
إذًا، مر الوقت وأتى الصباح،
I put a big, white sheet up, and I started to photograph these people.
فوضعت قماشة بيضاء كبيرة، وبدأت أصور الناس.
Suddenly, though, everything got a bit out of control,
فجأة، خرج كل شيء عن السيطرة،
and, although it was still dawn,
مع أن الوقت كان لا يزال فجرًا،
we were filled in this small little compound we had made
اكتظ المكان الصغير الذي صنعناه،
with literally hundreds of people turning up with ailments and diseases
حرفيًا، بمئات الأشخاص المصابين بالأمراض والأسقام
and just ... a hopeless situation.
وأصبح الأمر ... ميؤوسًا منه.
And that's exactly what their situation is -- helpless.
كما هو حال وضعهم بالضبط... فهم مغلوبون على أمرهم.
A child with a tumor that nobody helped, who was slowly suffocating.
فهذا طفل مصاب بورم ولم يساعده أحد، فكان يختنق ببطء.
I got in a bit of a panic,
أصابني شيء من الذعر،
because these people were coming up to me, desperate,
لأن هؤلاء الأشخاص كانوا يأتون إلي وهم يائسون
and I was trying to explain to the village elder
وكنت أحاول أن أشرح لكبير القرية
that I was not a doctor, and I couldn't help these people.
أني لست طبيبًا، ولا أستطيع مساعدة هؤلاء الأشخاص.
And the village elder turned to me and he said,
فالتفت إلي كبير القرية وقال:
"No, it's really important; these people know you're not a doctor,
" لا، ذلك مهم حقًا؛ فهؤلاء الأشخاص يعلمون أنك لست طبيبًا،
but at least somebody is now telling their story,
ولكن على الأقل هناك شخص ما يقوم بنقل قصتهم
and somebody is recording what is happening to them."
وتسجيل ما يحدث لهم."
And it was a good moment for me.
وكانت تلك لحظةً جيدةً لي.
It was a realization that maybe it was worthwhile
كانت لحظة إدراك بأنه لربما الخروج وفعل هذه الأمور
going off and doing these things.
هو أمر يستحق.
Another story that inspired me was in Odessa, in Ukraine.
قصة أخرى ألهمتني كانت في أوديسا بأوكرانيا.
I was documenting a bunch of street kids.
كنت أوثق قصة بعض من أطفال الشوارع.
I ended up actually living with them in a squat,
فانتهى بي الأمر بالعيش معهم،
which I can say was an experience.
ويمكنني أن أقول أنها كانت تجربة.
Many late nights of vodka-fueled violence
في العديد من الليالي كانت تنشب المشاكل بسبب كثرة شرب الفودكا
with me sitting in the corner with my bag,
بينما أنا جالس في الركن مع حقيبتي،
just going, "When was this a good idea?"
ولسان حالي يقول: " متى كانت هذه فكرة جيدة؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I would say it's moments like that when I think,
أستطيع القول أنه في لحظات مثل هذه أفكر
"Why did I leave the fashion world?"
"لماذا تركت عالم الأزياء؟"
But they were great kids,
ولكنهم كانوا رائعين،
and on the last day, they took me down to the sea
وفي اليوم الأخير، أخذوني إلى البحر
for a sort of trip, a sort of farewell.
كرحلة، كنوع من الوداع.
There they are, drinking vodka.
ها هم هناك، يشربون الفودكا.
And then Serge, who was the oldest and the most violent --
وهذا سيرج، الذي كان أكبرهم وأكثرهم عنفًا.
he'd just got out of the prison for stabbing somebody --
كان قد خرج من السجن للتو لطعنه شخصًا...
comes and puts his arm around me and says, "We go swimming."
يأتي إلي ويضع يده حولي ويقول: " لنذهب للسباحة."
Now, I have to say, I had a "Lonely Planet" guide to Ukraine
يجب علي الآن أن أقول، أنه كان لدي دليل "الكوكب الوحيد" لأوكرانيا
and in it, it gave some advice.
وبداخله، بعض النصائح.
And in that advice was, "Do not talk to the street kids,
إحداها كانت "لا تتحدث مع أطفال الشوارع،
at no point leave your baggage unattended
وأبدًا لا تترك أمتعتك بدون مراقبة،
and in all counts, do not go swimming."
وإياك أن تذهب للسباحة."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I was like, "I don't know if this is a good idea."
فكأن لسان حالي يقول: "لا أعلم إن كانت هذه فكرة جيدة."
Serge has got his arm around me.
كانت يد سيرج حولي.
I'm like, "OK." So there I am.
فقلت: "حسنًا".وها أنا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I literally handed all my cameras, all my equipment, to these street kids.
قمت بتسليم كل كاميراتي ومعداتي، لأطفال الشوارع هؤلاء.
And they took it.
وحملوها.
It's kind of funny to know, if you look in the background,
ومن المضحك، لو نظرت في الخلفية،
But one of the little kids, Lilic,
ولكن أحد الأطفال، ليلك،
he was the one who had taken my camera,
كان هو من أخذ الكاميرا الخاصة بي،
and he started taking photographs.
وبدأ بأخذ الصور.
He was really excited by this camera.
كان في غاية الحماس بهذه الكاميرا.
And we talked a lot about how I was going to get him a camera
وتحدثنا مطولاً عن كيف أني سأجلب له كاميرا
and would return and we could start to teach him photography.
وأني سأعود وأن بإمكاني أن أعلمه التصوير.
He had a real eye for things.
كانت لديه نظرة جيدة للأمور.
That's him, there.
هذا هو، هناك.
That was taken on the last evening I was there.
أُخذت هذه الصورة في آخر ليلة أمضيتها هناك.
I'd been staying there, but that night, I left to go and collect my things.
كنت أقيم هناك، ولكن في تلك الليلة، غادرت لأجمع أغراضي.
And when I came back in the morning, he was dead.
وعندما عدت في الصباح، كان قد مات.
He had taken a lot of pills and a lot of vodka.
كان قد تعاطى الكثير من المخدرات والفودكا.
And he had passed out in the night and didn’t recover.
وأُصيب بالإغماء في الليل ولم يستفق.
Again, it was another reminder
مرة أخرى، كان ذلك تذكير آخر
of maybe why I should record these people's stories:
بلماذا يجب علي أن أسجل قصص هؤلاء الناس
because their lives are important,
لأن حياتهم مهمة،
and it's important for me to document them.
ومن المهم لي تسجيلها.
Then in February of last year, when I was on patrol in Afghanistan,
ثم في فبراير من العام الماضي، حينما كنت في جولة في أفغانستان
I stepped on an IED.
دُست على عبوة ناسفة.
That's me down there, somewhere.
هذا أنا هناك، في مكان ما.
I became part of the story.
أصبحت جزءًا من القصة.
At first, I was devastated by what had happened, obviously.
في البداية، كنت محطمًا بسبب ما حدث، وهذا واضح.
I thought my work was over,
اعتقدت أن عملي انتهى،
I thought -- everything didn't make sense to me.
اعتقدت أن ما أفعله ليس له معنى.
And then I realized: I never set out to Congo,
ومن ثم أدركت، أنني لم أذهب أبدًا إلى الكونغو
to Angola, to Bangladesh
أو أنغولا أو بنغلاديش
to take photographs.
لالتقاط الصور.
I went to those places because I wanted to make some kind of change,
ولكن ذهبت لأني أود إحداث نوع من التغير،
and photography happened to be my tool.
وحدث أن كان التصوير وسيلتي.
And then I became aware that my body was, in many ways,
ومن ثم أدركت أن جسدي كان، بأكثر من طريقة،
a living example of what war does to somebody.
نموذج حي لما يمكن للحرب فعله بأي شخص.
And I realized I could use my own experience, my own body,
وأدركت أني أستطيع استخدام تجربتي وجسدي،
to tell that story.
لأروي قصة.
And it was also by looking back at the other people I've documented.
وكان ذلك أيضًا بنظري للوراء للأشخاص الذين قمت بتوثيقهم.
I thought of Nick, and I thought of his resilience.
فكرت في نيك، ومرونته.
I thought of the Rohingyas and the fact that they have no hope.
فكرت في الروهينجا وحقيقة أن لا أمل لديهم.
I thought of Lilic and a lost life.
فكرت في ليلك وحياته المفقودة.
And in fact, it was the stories that I've documented
وفي الواقع، كانت القصص التي وثقتها
that inspired me to get through the last year,
هي التي ألهمتني للبقاء خلال السنة الماضية،
to survive,
وللنجاة،
to get back up on my new legs
ولأقف مجددًا على أقدامي الجديدة
and to be able to come and tell their stories,
ولأتمكن من الذهاب وأروي قصصهم
but also my own story.
وقصتي أيصًا.
So I did a self-portrait,
فقمت بتصوير نفسي،
because I wanted to show everybody what a bomb does to somebody,
لأنني أردت أن أري الجميع ما تفعله القنبلة بالإنسان،
but also to show that losing your limbs doesn't end your life;
ولكن أيضًا لإظهار أن فقدان أطرافك لا ينهي حياتك.
that you can have what people say is disability,
وبأنه من الممكن أن يكون لديك ما يسميه الناس إعاقة،
but not be disabled;
ولا تكون معاقًا،
that you can be able to do anything
وأن بإمكانك فعل أي شيء
if you put your mind to it
إن ركزت فيه
and have belief in it.
وآمنت به.
It's strange,
قد يبدو هذا غريبًا،
but in many ways I look at where I was a year ago,
ولكن بطرق كثيرة أنظر حيث كُنت منذ سنة،
and I look at where I am now,
وما أنا عليه الآن،
and I realize that I have a lot of things I didn't have then.
وأدرك أن لدي أمورًا كثيرة لم تكن لدي من قبل.
I wouldn't be sitting here right now if this hadn't happened.
فلم أكن لأجلس هنا لو لم يحدث هذا.
I wouldn't have been able to show you those photographs
ولم أكن لأستطيع عرض هذه الصور عليكم
I was lucky 10 years ago, when I sat down and I tried to work out
كنت محظوظا منذ 10 سنوات، حين توقفت وحاولت معرفة
what I could do to make a difference in this world.
ما يمكنني فعلة لتغيير هذا العالم.
I realized that my photography was a tool and a way to do it.
أدركت أن تصويري كان أداة وطريقة لفعل ذلك.
I think that's what's really key.
أعتقد أن المهم حقًا.
It's that we all can be part of that wheel.
هو أن بإمكاننا جميعاً أن نكون جزء من هذه العجلة.
We can all be cogs in a wheel of change.
بإمكاننا أن نكون تروسًا في عجلة التغير.
We can all make a difference.
نستطيع جميعًا إحداث تغيير.
Everybody here has an ability to use something
كل شخص هنا لديه القدرة علي استخدام شيء
to make a difference to the world.
لإحداث تغير في العالم.
We can all sit in front of the TV and go,
نستطيع جميعًا أن نجلس أمام التلفاز ونقول:
"I don't know what to do about it," and forget about it.
"لا أعلم ما يمكنني فعله،" وأن ننسى الأمر.
But the reality is that we can all do something.
ولكن الواقع أننا نستطيع جميعًا فعل شيء.
It might be just writing a letter.
قد يكون فقط كتابة رسالة.
It might be standing on a soapbox and talking.
أو الوقوف على منصة والتحدث.
It might be just recording somebody's story
قد يكون توثيق قصة شخص ما
and telling it to somebody else.
وإخبارها لشخص آخر.
But every single one of us here,
ولكن كل شخص منا هنا،
if we want to make a difference, we can, an there is nothing to stop us.
لو أراد إحداث تغيير، سيستطيع، وليس هناك ما يمنعه.
And we all have our own experiences that we can use as well.
ولدينا جميعًا خبراتنا الخاصة التي نستطيع استخدامها أيضًا.
So really, that's all I wanted to talk about today.
إذًا، هذا كل ما أردت الحديث عنه اليوم.
I just wanted to say that life goes on all around the world.
أردت فقط أن أقول أن الحياة تستمر في أنحاء العالم.
People are going through terrible things.
ويمر الناس بأمور فظيعة.
Everyone of us is going through our own terrible experience.
كل شخص منا يمر بتجربته الفظيعة الخاصة.
But if we share those and we talk about stories,
ولكن لو شاركنها وتحدثنا عن هذه القصص،
then we can inspire each other
عندها نستطيع إلهام بعضنا البعض
to get through our own bad experiences.
لنتجاوز تجاربنا السيئة.
I know that the people I've recorded have gotten me to this point.
أعلم أن الناس الذين قمت بتسجيل قصصهم هم من أوصلوني لهذه النقطة.
And I hope in some small way, the stories I've been able to tell you
وأتمنى ولو بشكل بسيط، أن تكون هذه القصص التي أخبرتكم بها
will help you get through things.
ستساعدكم على تجاوز الأمور.
And in turn, I hope you will use your experiences to help others.
وبالمقابل، أتمنى أن تقوموا باستخدام تجاربكم لمساعدة الآخرين.
Thank you very much.
شكرًا جزيلًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)